Finding Aid for Michigan Roundtable for Diversity and Inclusion records, 1941-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Roundtable for Diversity and Inclusion records
1941-2011
Michigan Roundtable for Diversity and Inclusion.
0703 Ba 2; Ba Out
Organization established to promote values of religious and racial tolerance; scrapbooks, program files, records of the women’s division, and photographs.
9 linear feet
21 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from the organization (donor no. 9823 ) in December 2006. Additions were received in 2012.
The record group is open to research.
The National Conference of Christians and Jews was founded in 1928 "to promote justice, amity, understanding and cooperation among Protestants, Catholics and Jews .... with a view to the establishment of a social order in which the religious ideals of brotherhood and justice shall become the standards of human relationships."
The Detroit Council of Catholics, Jews and Protestants was organized early in 1940 with its name soon changed to the Detroit Round Table of Catholics, Jews and Protestants. Members of the Council's organization committee included Henry Hitt Crane and Leo M. Franklin. Impetus for the organization in this pre-war period was the growth of totalitarianism abroad and divisions within the Detroit community inflamed by such preachers/politicians as Gerald L.K. Smith and Father Coughlin. The aim of the Round Table was to foster religious and racial brotherhood and to counter those who would divide the community on religious or racial lines. Programs of the organization included seminars, workshops, lectures, dinners, and such events as the annual Brotherhood Week observances.
The organization has undergone several name changes in its history reflecting changes in scope and objectives. At present, the records do not make clear the precise dates of these changes. The organization was first the Detroit Round Table. It later became the Greater Detroit Round Table of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, then the Greater Detroit Interfaith Round Table, the National Conference for Community and Justice of Michigan, and then in 2006, the Michigan Roundtable for Diversity and Inclusion.
The records have been arranged into the following series: Scrapbooks; Program files; Women’s Division of the Greater Detroit Round Table; Photographs; Board of Directors; Different People…Common Ground workshop; and Miscellaneous. Although the records date from approximately 1941 to 2011, the individual series do not cover this span and thus a full record of the organization’s history is missing.
Subjects:
Michigan Roundtable for Diversity and Inclusion.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Religious tolerance--Michigan.; Social integration--Michigan.; Women--Societies and clubs--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series includes clippings, programs, and other materials about the activities of the Round Table, but they date only from 1942 to 1952. There are several files of loose clippings for subsequent years, but not all of these are specific to the organization's activities.
  - July 1942-April 1943 (Volume 1)
  - May 1943-March 1944 (Volume 2)
  - March 1944-December 1944 (Volume 3)
  - December 1944-April 1945 (Volume 4)
  - May 1945-September 1945 (Volume 5)
  - September 1945-January 1946 (Volume 6)
  - January 1946-June 1946 (Volume 7)
  - June 1946-October 1946 (Volume 8)
  - October 1946-January 1947 (Volume 9)
  - February 1947-May 1947 (Volume 10)
  - May 1947-September 1947 (Volume 11)
  - October 1947-January 1948 (Volume 12)
  - February 1948-November 1948 (Volume 13)
  - September 1948-December 1948 (Volume 14)
  - January 1949-November 1949 (Volume 15)
  - Testimonial dinner, 1948 (Volume 16)
  - Brotherhood Week
    - 1947 (Volume 17)
    - 1948 (Volume 18)
    - 1950 (Volume 19)
    - 1951 (Volume 20)
    - 1952 (Volume 21)
  - Contents of scrapbook relating to anti-Semitism, the America First movement, 1941-1947; 3 folders (Box 5)
    (include clippings, articles, and publications)
  - Clippings, circa 1959-1970s; 9 folders (Box 5)
    (probably intended to be placed in scrapbooks)
- Program files
  The Program files describe some of the activities in the late 1970s and the work of the American Arabic and Jewish Friends of Metropolitan Detroit beginning in 1992.
  - Mailings with program announcements, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Program reports, 1977-1980; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - American Arabic and Jewish Friends of Metropolitan Detroit
    - Scholarship Dinner, 1992-1997 (Box 1)
    - Essay contents (Box 1)
    - Mailing list (Box 1)
  - Brotherhood / Humanitarian Tribute Dinners (programs), 1998-2006 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder Ba Outsize)
  - Newsletters, 1983-1991; 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - National Conference for Community and Justice
    - Report of the NCCJ TASK Force on Sexual Orientation and Human Relations, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Anniversary CD-ROM: "The First 75 Years", 2007; 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 1)
      (include articles and photographs)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Women's Division of the Greater Detroit Round Table
  The scrapbooks of Women's Division of the Greater Detroit Round Table cover the period of 1952 to 1992 and are organized by name of the president of the Division. These scrapbooks include many photographs of Division activities.
  - Scrapbooks containing clippings, programs photographs, and other records of activities, 1952-1985 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks containing clippings, programs photographs, and other records of activities, 1984-1992 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series is arranged in approximate chronological order (as much is undated). The Photographs (1945-1988) depict activities sponsored by the Round Table, including dinners, community programs, radio and television broadcasts, and general publicity.
  - Photographs depicting activities and programs, 1945-1988 (Box 4)
- Board of Directors
  - Agenda, minutes, committee reports, memoranda, and related materials, 2001-2009 (Box 6)
  - Agenda, minutes, committee reports, memoranda, and related materials, 2001-2009 (Box 7)
    (continued)
- Different People...Common Ground workshop
  - Diversity training curriculum, handouts, facilitator materials, 2006 (Box 8)
  - Wayne State University School of Medicine, Diversity Day training, 2002-2006 (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Walk2gether event (Box 9)
  - Annual Symposium, 1992-1997 (Box 9)
  - Resource materials, publicity, speech materials, clippings (Box 9)
    (The files are unarranged)